PRATIK MULTANI

250 Main Street, Hartford, CT 06106 pratik.multani@uconn.edu (959) 999-2806 linkedin.com/in/pratik-multani-2818a21b2/

Have 4+ years of experience in using the trifecta of domain expertise, statistical analysis, and computer science knowledge to deliver actionable business solutions and narrate compelling stories to sell the ideas that drive the solution. To structure my analysis, I rely on my experiences with Data Wrangling, Exploratory Data Analysis (EDA), Data Modeling, and Data Mining.

Professional Experience

ZS Associates (Pune, India) - Data Analyst Associate Consultant

May 2018 - Aug 2021

Project: Choice Hotels: Revenue Optimization | Data-Driven Decision Making | Data Management | Statistical Analysis

- Worked as a revenue data analyst, formulating, and implementing data-driven sales strategies for a hotel portfolio of 40+ hotels generating \$30Mil. annual revenue
- Used machine learning algorithms (regression and random forest) in python to model the impact of independent variables on sales. Used the insights to develop focused strategies to grow portfolio revenue by 7% in 2019
- Developed SQL queries using ETL process to extract data and load into Excel/Tableau; Created Dashboards to highlight trends and identified KPI in response to business requirements
- Optimized web traffic by using web analytics data provided by Google Analytics and Expedia improving conversion rate by 5%
- Employed A/B testing to identify the accurate pricing differential between room types for various hotels leading to an increase in revenue of focus group properties by 4%
- Demonstrated the effectiveness of implemented strategies using uplift analysis. Developed best practices based on identified trends in Uplift analysis

Project: Microsoft: Sales Alignment | Data Visualization | Business Intelligence Reporting | Business Analytics

- Optimized and operationalized assignment of global accounts to suitable CSM using Excel, power queries and VBA
- Forecasted future account count in SAS using time series forecasting models to facilitate future hiring planning
- Migrated periodic summary and insights reporting to python (Google Colaboratory/Jupyter) reducing response time by 33%

Thyssenkrupp Electrical Steel (Nashik, India) - Quality Assurance Engineer

Aug 2017 - Apr 2018

- Randomly sampled the processed coil; performed hypothesis testing to ascertain the core losses for the processed coil are within guaranteed tolerances
- Performed matched pair hypothesis testing to improve the efficiency of laser by optimizing processing parameters of grainoriented electrical steel reducing the effective mean core losses by 8%

Academic Projects

Predictive Analytics and Survival Analytics | Customer Churn for Credit Service

- Implemented EDA to explore the data structure, drew insights about customer behavior and factors affecting their churn
- Used random under-sampling to shape the data; employed **bootstrap forest** for max. prediction accuracy of churned customers
- Recommended strategies to encourage retention based on the insights from the model
- Conduct survival analysis to estimate customer churn time and establish urgency in deploying retention strategies

Technical Skills

Programming Language: MySQL | Oracle SQL | R | Python (NumPy, Pandas, Matplotlib, Scikit learn, Seaborn) | SAS

Tools: MS Excel | VBA | Tableau | MS Office Suite | MS Project | Power BI | Power Query | Google Analytics

Analytics: Supervised and Unsupervised Machine Learning Algorithm | Clustering (K means, Hierarchal) | Data Enrichment |
Linear/Logistic Regression | K-NN | Random Forests | Gradient Boosting | Neural Networks | Hypothesis testing | Confidence
Interval | Segmentation | Customer Analytics | A/B testing | Market Basket Analysis | Time Series Forecasting | Survival Analysis

Education

University of Connecticut School of Business | Aug 2021 – Present | MS in Business Analytics & Project Management | GPA 3.94/4 Visvesvaraya National Institute of Technology, Nagpur, India | Jul 2013 – May 2017 | B. Tech in Metallurgical Eng. | GPA: 9.04/10

Awards & Achievements

- Awarded Innovator of the Quarter twice for developing tools to facilitate faster and accurate revenue analysis
- Certified Revenue Management Executive by HSMAI
- Awarded scholarship (OPJEMS) for entrepreneurial and innovative excellence